Hello! In today's Bug Bounty Report Explained,
you will learn how it was possible to hack
Facebook in not one but three different ways.
Those vulnerabilities were submitted across
two reports for which the researcher,
Alaa Abdulridha, got $55,000 in total.
Links to the original blogposts
are in the description.
Enjoy! So there were two blogposts by the same
author. In part one, he found an application
legal.tapprd.facebook.com. There was
no registration but he found a hidden
endpoint /savepassword which allowed him to take
over arbitrary account. From javascript files
he prepared a valid body and then
brute-forced the list of usernames.
The endpoint allowed changing anyone's password,
provided that we know their username. So it was
complete account takeover. During his brute
force he hit one correct username to prepare
the proof of concept. He reported the bug and got
$7,500 for it. But he wanted more. His idea was
to test session management. He had to
look into his burp history to see what was
going on when he was testing for the first
vulnerability. He noticed ASPXAUTH cookie.
It's a default cookie name from standard .NET's
FormAuthentication class. It works this way:
there is this thing called ticket which contains
your data that you want to be stored inside the
cookie. Usually, it's data that can identify
the user, for example username or user id.
First, the ticket in cleartext is signed using
SHA-1 algorithm. Then, the whole ticket along
with the signature is encrypted and then the
encrypted block is signed again using SHA-1. SHA-1
is a default algorithm for signing while AES is a
standard encryption algorithm. The developer must
set at least two keys: validationKey for signing
and decryptionKey for encryption and decryption
of the data. The typical flow looks like this:
when you successfully log into the application,
some of your data is being put in this cookie
and this cookie is sent with your every request.
And upon every request the application
must validate the first signature,
decrypt the cookie and validate the second
signature. At the end, it decodes your username
or user id from the ticket and it confirms
that it's actually you. If something goes
wrong along the way, you are not authenticated.
Keys are sufficiently strong so that the cookie
is not brute-forceable. There is also no known
way to disclose those keys. But the bughunter
assumed that this application is vulnerable
once he saw this cookie name. Why was that?
The documentation tells you to just provide the
username. No user id, no application id, nothing
like this. And what's important, your username
is shared across many different applications.
Is that a problem? It's not until you use
different keys for different websites.
And according to the blogpost only 20% of
applications do this properly and 80% of them
are vulnerable. I find this number a bit hard
to believe but I have never myself tested for
this vulnerability. The attack looks like this:
you have application 1 to which you can't log in.
It uses ASPXAUTH cookie to identify the user.
Then, you find the second application that must
also use the ASPXAUTH cookie, but
this website must allow registration.
Those applications must be related - running
on the same server. For this attack to work,
you must know the username from user from
app 1 whose account you will take over.
In our case, the bughunter brute-forced
the username during the first attack.
Now, if a validationKey and decryptionKey
are shared across those two applications
you can take the victim's login from app 1 and
sign up using this username to up to app 2.
After logging in, app 2 will sign your cookie
and encrypt it and then sign it once again.
Then, you copy this cookie from app
2 to app 1. App 1 will successfully
validate and decrypt the cookie, because
keys are shared between those applications.
Then, the application will take the ticket which
was inside the cookie. There is no application id
that mismatches here, there is no unique user id.
There is only the username, so app1 logs you in
with that username, finishing our arbitrary
account takeover. That's exactly what the hunter
did here. Unfortunately, details of the second
application are not disclosed in the blogpost.
If you are like me, right now you are wondering
how did this happen that developers from such
a big company just copied the keys from one app
to another. But turns out they probably didn't.
By default, keys are not created manually,
but auto-generated using machineKey Element.
And those keys are derived from the
machine properties, so if you have
multiple websites running on the same server,
they will have the same keys. To avoid that,
you need to use isolateApps modifier which makes
the key being generated using the application id.
At least that's what one page
from the documentation says.
The other page says that it only uses virtual
paths. This would work if you would have one
domain and one application would work under / path
and the other would work under /app2. They would
have different virtual paths, thus different keys.
But in today's world it's not the most common use
case. More likely, your two applications will work
on two different ports, let's say 8080 and 8081.
Then, you would have a reverse proxy that
routes the traffic from one domain to port 8080
and the traffic to other domain to port 8081.
The customer only uses port 443 on both domains.
But coming back to our app isolation, both of them
in such case would have / as their virtual path.
So if isolate apps modifier was used, keys
will still be exactly the same across those
applications. As this is the default setting I'd
assume that's what happened with Facebook. The
fix for that is changing isolateApps modifier
to isolateByAppId which actually uses the app
id. This is a typical example of insecure by
default and I wouldn't even put much blame on
the developers - no way they could see this coming
reading this documentation. Even for me, when I
knew exactly what am I looking for, it took a few
hours to dig deep to find all this information.
So he could get another $7,500 for that, but it
wasn't enough. This time, he wanted to go further.
He asked for permission to test for SSRFs because
there was a functionality that brought his
attention: API trigger. It was pretty much SSRF
by design - you could make requests anywhere.
Facebook gave him green light to test for this. It
even has an internal endpoint that you can request
to show the proof of concept of your SSRF. So
he created a custom script in some editor that
allowed him to make requests to arbitrary URLs,
but also with arbitrary headers and arbitrary
methods. It's important, because Facebook SSRF
guidelines say that for SSRF when you can read
responses, you get $40,000 but if you can control
the whole request, including headers, you get
$5,000 bonus. In total, he got $54,800 for those
two reports. Quite a good payout if you ask me.
And that's it. I myself didn't know about this
ASPXAUTH cookie before and even searching strictly
for that I didn't find many sources about it.
Considering that FormAuthentication class is
a part .NET's standard security module, it's
probably quite common. So if you also didn't
know about this, leave a like under this video.
Also, sign up for my mailing list to be the first
to know about any of my future projects.
For now, thank you for watching and goodbye!